In this video, we're
going to just introduce
the concept of quantitative risk analysis.
Now, quantitative risk analysis then is
basically analyzing your risks using an
actual dollar value, right, an actual
dollar value.
And we're going to basically be creating
or we're going to be calculating something
called expected monetary value,
EMV.
Now more about that
in just a second, I just
want to first mention
this exam tip, right?
I know we've mentioned it in previous
videos as well, but again, I just want to
reiterate because this is very,
very important.
Do not confuse qualitative risk analysis
and quantitative risk analysis.
They both sound very, very similar.
If you look at the spelling,
the spelling looks very
similar, but they are two
very different processes.
With qualitative risk analysis,
you are analysing your risk and you are
ranking and prioritising your risk based
on arbitrary values, high, medium low,
scale of 1 to 10, you know, any other
arbitrary value.
With quantitative, we are actually putting
in a dollar value to our risk.
We're actually adding in some absolute
values.
Dollar value, it could be a scheduling
impact, right?
It could be a impact to our resources.
So that is what quantitative is.
So make sure when you are reading an exam
question, especially when you're two hours
or three hours into an exam, it's very,
very easy to misread.
So let's talk about quantitative then,
quantitative risk analysis.
Now, remember, a risk is an uncertainty.
It may happen.
It may not happen.
And you can have a positive risk or you
could have a negative risk.
But when you're coming up with a risk,
right, when you're identifying,
well, there's going to be some kind of
actual, you know, impact to the risk,
meaning there could be
a dollar impact, it could be
a timeline, it could be a
resource impact, right?
So as a very simple example then.
If, you know, if material
prices increases, then there's
going to have a dollar
impact on our project, right?
So we've identified, or material prices
might increase.
If material prices
increases by this much, then
this will have a $20,000
impact on our project.
We'll end up having to spend an additional
$20,000 in our project, right?
If it happens, right, or it could be a
scheduling impact, right?
If vendor delay shipment of raw materials,
right, then, you know, we may end up
delaying our project by a week,
right, or two weeks.
We may end up going behind schedule.
Or there might be some additional
resource.
it might impact a resource.
So if we realize that this activity is
bigger than what we were expecting,
we might need some additional team members
to work on this task.
So that's all negative.
It could also be a positive risk.
What if material prices come down?
There's a chance of material
prices might come down, in
which case then we might end
up actually saving some money.
So this is all then quantitative risk
analysis, actually adding some kind of
dollar value or having some kind of actual
specific impact on our project,
whether it's a schedule impact,
whether it's a monetary impact.
Now, as a general rule, though,
if they're asking you to do any
calculations on the exam, usually it's
going to be from a monetary perspective.
Generally, it's going to be from a
monetary perspective.
And the formula is the same as what we saw
in the qualitative risk
analysis discussion.
It's exactly the same formula.
It's still probability times impact,
except this time it's your dollar impact.
probability times whatever your dollar
impact is or your monetary impact and that
equals something called EMV expected
monetary value.
Formal is very simple right and we're
going to be covering some calculations on
this in a separate video but it's
literally probability in the exam they
will always give your probability and the
probability will generally be in the form
of a percentage times your impact your
dollar impact right your monetary impact
again they will always give you that on
the exam and that equals your EMV expected
monetary value so you just multiply the
two numbers together and that gives you
your EMV so again we've got some
calculations on this on a separate video okay